Kent, England

Ian Morgan

https://www.linkedin.com/in/ianjmorgan https://github.com/ianmorgan

Development Manager, Architect, Developer and occasional DevOps specializing in agile, small teams, DDD, Event Sourcing, CQRS and Microservices. Ian has worked in the IT Industry since graduating as an engineer, with wide ranging experiences in roles, industries and technologies, from Ruby on Rails to a touch of Scala and Clojure.

A believer in keeping designs simple and componentized, Ian likes to start from the business problems and real-world constraints rather than the technology. Many businesses would benefit from the buzzwords above and much else, but it is rarely clear how at the beginning. Find a way to communicate with stakeholders and users first, be that BDD specs, wireframes, domain models, process model, event storming and work back from that.

Implementation language(s) and tools should preferably match the characteristics of the system being built, as they will end up driving a lot of the team culture.

Skills

- Technical Management
- Microservices
- CQRS, DDD & Event Sourcing

- JVM Based Development
- Data Centric Applications
- Pragmatic Testing

Experience

OCTOBER 2015 - MAY 2015

Head of Development / Mirriad, London

Grew small development team to 14, delivering the first release of the "Marketplace" system, which connects worldwide customers to Mirriad's platform. Assisted the CTO and CEO in defining key requirements and de-facto product owner to the development team until a product management team was established. Managed and actively assisted in the DevOps for 40+ Microservices, deployed to both AWS and Alibaba Cloud in China. Working with 2 team leads and project manager to build stable Scrum/Kanban style development process.

MARCH 2015 - SEPTEMBER 2015

Team Lead / Mirriad, London

Very "hands on" leading of a small team of Java & front-end developers building a Microservices platform. Established Docker deployment processes and updated architecture to use CQRS & Event Sourcing principles in the more complex areas.

MAY 2012 - FEB 2015

Senior Developer / Can Factory, London

Senior developer on Cineworld website. Integrated SOLR search engine, built internal log analysis tools in Scala, application development in Java & Spring plus technical support to operations team.

Architect / consultant for JATO Dynamic, a major supplier of data to the automotive industry. Leading a small internal team to help design a new platform. Responsibilities included requirement analysis, development of prototypes in Groovy and Scala and data architecture.

Active in assisting management team with bids and proposals.

MARCH 2011 - MARCH 2012

Senior Java Developer / Dept of Transport, Melbourne

Working on the Performance Reporting System for the Metropolitan rail network, built using Java using Spring, JSF, JPA and Drools. Responsibilities were domain modelling, data matching tools in Ruby, implementing BDD style tests in Groovy and resolving Java and SQL performance problems.

OCTOBER 2010 - DECEMBER 2010

Web Developer / Australia Post, Melbourne

Full stack developer for new online system, developed using Grails and aggressive use of BDD.

OCTOBER 2009 - OCTOBER 2010

Backend Java Developer / Australia Post, Melbourne

A greenfield system for processing passport style applications (where there is a need to securely capture and exchange biographic data and identity documents). Ian's role was the design and development of Java backend components for system integration, message translation and workflow management. Integration points included .NET, Adobe Flex, JAXB, Portal Severs, jBPM, and TIBCO.

2006 - 2009

Contract Java & Web Developer / Various, Melbourne

Several contract roles combined with travel back to the UK and stay at home parenting. Some highlights include a large development for ANZ Bank run by ThoughWorks to classic agile and TDD, building a desktop Java app, and the redevelopment of the public web site for BUPA. Lowlights include encapsulating legacy EJBs within a JSF layer.

2003 - 2006

Online Service Architect / Dept of Justice, Melbourne

A role that combined operational support of the transactional website while working on strategic projects including a government wide directory service and the Department's e-Business strategy.

1998 - 2003

Senior Consultant / Logica, Melbourne

lan worked as a senior consultant in development, architecture and team lead roles. Achievements include establishing the first online transactions for the Department of Justice, designing a custom data matching solution for maintaining electoral rolls, building two greenfield system, finding the bug that had been bringing seek.com.au down for a week and the first Java application on a major superannuation platform.

1994 - 1998

Consultant / Logica (Admiral Computing), Camberley

Ian worked on projects in the retail and commercial banking sector. Projects ranged from PC applications written in Visual Basic, C++ and RPC to an early web platform for a major bank. A key contribution was the ability to stabilize what was often quite new or even beta technology.

1993 - 1994

Windows Developer / Miles 33, Bracknell

Miles 33 provided a variety of IT solutions to the publishing and newspaper industry. These include typesetting systems, editorial systems and advertisement management systems. Ian's roles were design and development on Windows applications in C++ (MFC) and customer support.

1987 - 1993

PC Developer / Promicro, London

Building PC based software for the real-time monitoring of storage facilities, primarily for the petrochemical industry. The systems were developed in Pascal, C/C++ and Assembler, with versions running on DOS and OS/2. Ian was involved in all aspects of design and implementation and in site visits for installation and testing.

Education

1983 - 1986

BSc Mechanical Engineering / University of Southampton

The discipline of engineering is useful, but the maths and theory is very stale now.

Q4 2014

Mining Massive Dataset / Stanford University, Online

From the classic supermarket "beer next to nappies" insight to recommendation engines and Google page rank. Proud of myself to complete it (with distinction) as it counts for a complete module in a Stanford degree. No use at all in my last role, which is a shame, though I knew that at the time.

Activities

When I have more time and live closer to the sea, I will go back to falling of a surfboard. For now cycling and incorrect Yoga poses keep the body from total collapse, and family and children keep me busy. I try to keep up to date with selective technologies, GraphQL and Kotlin are my thing at present.